Now, listen.
Dervahl's planning something big in Meridian.
He said he'd force Avad to watch as the smoke darkens their precious Sun.
Your king needs you.
No more playing around.
You're gonna have to grow up fast.
I will, I promise.
You damn well better little brother.
Ersa!
No, no! Please!
I won't let you down.
I promise.
[Carja merchant]
The machines grow more bloodthirsty every day.
The Sun is still displeased.
[Carja artisan]
Eh, I've seen better.
Oh, that's nice. Glad I stopped for a bit.
[Carja guard]
Some Oseram girl applied to the City Guard the other day…
There are no shadows under the noonday sun. Words to live by.
[Carja guard]
It's not what I imagined when I was a boy, but it's decent work keeping the city safe.
[Carja merchant]
Don't pass up these goods!
[Carja guard]
It's always the ones you least expect that cause the trouble.
[Carja merchant]
Come take a look, I'll give you a good price.
You won't find better wares.
[Carja outlander]
Most of the commoners…
Women rising in the ranks of the Hunters Lodge? A real lady…
[Carja outlander]
The Sundom was founded here…
Talanah, always a pleasure.
I see you've brought your pet.
Greetings, Sunhawk.
I hereby sponsor Aloy of the Nora for membership in the Hunters Lodge.
No! Look at her.
She's low born, a savage.
This is beneath even you, Talanah.
She has fulfilled the requirements.
And Sun-King Avad decreed the Lodge should be open to all.
Would you like to take it up with him?
The word of the Sun-King is indeed law.
Even though it will bring ruin to the Lodge, so be it.
Do you, Aloy of the Nora, pledge to act rightly and nobly
when in service to the Lodge all the days to follow?
I do.
Members of the Lodge, even though Tarkas is barely cold,
I present to you Aloy of the Nora, member and Thrush.
What say you all?
To the hunt!
Sponsoring an outlander.
While you make meaningless gestures, I'll be finding Redmaw.
This, this is a good day.
What's Redmaw?
Few have seen it.
A Thunderjaw marked by years of battle.
Some say it still bears the marks of over a dozen hunters on its flank.
How many it has trampled along the way we may never know.
When members go hunting and never return, we often blame Redmaw.
But to me it's more than legend.
It's the only machine that will unseat Ahsis.
My sponsor nearly had it, but…
He didn't make it.
I'm sorry.
Tarkas sponsored me out of loyalty to my family.
He was my last link to them, besides the Lodge itself.
I have to unseat Ahsis.
I know why I hate Ahsis. Why do you?
My family has always boasted members in the Lodge.
My father and brother were both Hawks.
Ahsis let their sacrifice be forgotten.
Um, what sacrifice?
They died in the massacre.
They should be honoured as Hawks.
Instead Ahsis will not let anyone mention it.
What happened?
King Jiran's paranoia knew no bounds.
He sent thousands of innocents to die in the Sun Ring.
When the Hawks of the Lodge called for him to stop the slaughter,
he threw them in the ring too.
Yet when the machines attacked the condemned,
more Hawks leapt into the ring to defend them.
My father and brother were among them.
I'm…
I'm so sorry.
If you wish to hear the story Ligan can tell it better.
He saw it with his own eyes.
I did not.
The morning of the massacre my father told me to meet him outside the city.
He told me they were planning an escape.
I waited for hours until a message came from my father.
I had to leave the city.
So I fled when I should have fought by his side.
He didn't want you to die with them.
Nor would he want their names forgotten.
Especially by the man who benefited most from their deaths.
Ahsis.
How did your family come to be members of the Lodge?
Carja noble houses have sent sons to the Lodge for generations.
Because you need another place to lord over the commoners.
I want to change that.
The idea that someone is worthy or not by virtue of birth alone.
Everyone thinks they have me pegged as soon as they hear Talanah Khane Padish.
I hate that.
I understand.
My whole life I lived as an outcast from the Nora.
They would have been the first to say I wasn't one of them.
I didn't know.
Yet as soon as I leave the Sacred Land, everyone calls me Aloy of the Nora.
It should be Aloy despite the Nora.
You should improve your reputation.
Why don't you hunt down a Thunderjaw and a Stormbird.
You want me to go trophy hunting?
You're not just any Thrush, you're mine.
And you'd better make me look good.
But what about Redmaw?
Don't worry. I won't take on Redmaw without you.
I must say I'm surprised by your achievements.
Bringing in a Stalker already.
Save your surprise.
I'm just getting started.
Two new Thrushes in one day, makes a Hawk proud.
Thrushes are members sponsored by a Hawk.
They can't become a Hawk until their sponsor leaves, or passes away.
The Hawk who brings in the trophy from the fiercest machine is the Sunhawk.
He serves as ceremonial leader of the Lodge.
So now that Talanah is a Hawk, she could become Sunhawk?
Yes.
If she defeats Redmaw before Ahsis can, then she will take his place.
What exactly is Redmaw?
The meanest of all Thunderjaws.
Some say the first.
One swipe of its tail and five hunters go down.
Its stomps can send boulders tumbling before it.
More than a few have been crushed under their weight.
And thus, many have died trying to defeat it.
If Redmaw is so deadly, why do hunters keep going after it?
Anyone who defeats this beast will surely be considered a champion.
I watched Tarkas try his luck.
He jumped over each tail swipe, dodged every charge, evaded every shot from its gun.
Stumbling under its feet, he ran out to fire at range.
But it unleashed disc launchers.
The first missed him, but not the second.
Who was Tarkas?
Tarkas, Sun light his passing, was a Hawk.
A respected hunter.
He sponsored Talanah many years ago.
If Talanah was his Thrush, why did he fight Redmaw without her?
I went to watch the battle.
She should have received word he'd picked up its trail.
Someone at the Lodge failed to pass it on.
Can you tell me what happened during the massacre?
A terrible time.
King Jiran purged loyal subjects and traitors alike throughout the Sundom.
Even called out members of our Lodge.
Why?
Some spoke out against the killing.
And when the soldiers came for them we all objected.
And for that crime those who were not arrested were forced to watch our comrades murdered in the Sun Ring.
I shouldn't say more.
Please, tell me what happened that day in the Sun Ring.
Normally, victims of the Sun Ring fell within minutes as the crowd cheered.
Cheered their deaths, but not with our Hawks.
They stood alone against wave after wave of machines.
Hours passed, the men taking turns fighting as the others rested.
The crowd's mood turned, rallying around our men.
Some of them left, their bloodlust unsated.
We members stayed and watched 'til nightfall.
It was then the court released a Behemoth.
Several Hawks at once jumped into the ring to fight alongside the condemned.
They had snuck in their weapons.
I wish I had as well.
The machine didn't discriminate.
It crashed into the stand, devastating spectator and fighter alike.
It was a slaughter.
And how did the battle in the Sun Ring come to an end?
Talanah's father climbed atop a Behemoth and with one well-placed spear, destroyed it.
Just as a second knocked him to his death.
Her brother and the others fought this second Behemoth, falling one by one,
as they put themselves between the beast and the stands.
And so we and the spectators were saved.
Those who had once cheered for their deaths
thanked the dying men for their very lives.
What a brave end.
And how terrible that no one speaks of it.
Be careful out there.
Thank you.
I should be on my way.
Keep hunting, Thrush!
[Carja merchant]
…stopping when you're in the thick of it.
[Carja noble]
The Vanguard serve the Carja, whether they like it or not.
[Oseram merchant]
There's plenty of work here…
[Carja merchant]
Let's have a chat.
No, a colourful discussion.
[Carja guard]
Don't let your guard down.
I was a guard under the last king…
[Carja guard]
It's not what I imagined when I was a boy, but it's decent work…
[Erend]
I've sent a messenger to The Claim to let everyone know.
[Avad]
If there's anything you or your clan need for her arrangements, you need but ask.
[Erend]
There'll be time for all of that later.
Aloy, I'm glad you're back.
I'm at a loss about Ersa.
To learn she lives then lose that hope seems cruel.
She wouldn't want us to waste time talking.
She'd want us to find Dervahl.
She said he raved about smoke darkening the sun.
Tell him what you found in his papers.
A letter.
It mentioned a shipment of Blaze being sent to a warehouse here.
Only it wasn't addressed to Dervahl.
The name was Aelund Forgeman.
Does that mean anything to you?
Uh, sounds familiar.
Yes, a landlord.
The Oseram have been buying up buildings across the city,
including one under that name.
Let me think, it's by the edge of the mesa, near the temple.
Used to be a shop, but it could serve as a warehouse.
If Dervahl used the name is an alias to buy it, he might even be there now.
I'll round up my men.
I'll meet you there.
Erend, wait.
Remember that no-one hates Dervahl more than your own tribe.
The clans would give up much to obtain him.
Take him alive so you can haggle over him?
You can't be serious!
Our security depends on keeping the peace.
If the opportunity presents itself, take him alive.
Consider that a command.
Grr!
Aloy, a moment, please.
When we spoke, Erend didn't wish to dwell on the details of Ersa's death.
Understandable, of course.
But now that they've been left to my imagination,
those details are all I can think about.
You were there.
Did she suffer?
She's not the one who's suffering now.
You are.
She died before you could say goodbye.
Is it that obvious?
You're right.
I'm dwelling on my pain.
Not just hers.
She wasn't worried about her pain.
She was worried about her brother, and she was worried about you.
Thank you Aloy.
All that matters is that we catch her killer before he strikes again.
How much like her you sound.
You are correct, of course.
Find Dervahl and bring him before me.
He will answer for his crimes.
[Carja merchant]
Don't pass up these goods.
Could you spare a moment to speak of the finer things?
[Vilgund]
Able bodied adventurers!
Preferably with no friends or family, but I'm not choosy.
[Erend]
This is the place.
You home Dervahl? I got a surprise for you!
[Aloy]
Blaze.
[Erend]
Is it a bomb? Doesn't look too big.
[Aloy]
Big enough to kill us.
[Erend]
All right, I'll shut up.
It's a bomb, alright.
If I try to take it apart, a booby trap will set it off.
It must be leaking from something upstairs.
[Erend]
That's a lot of Blaze.
[Aloy]
If that bomb downstairs goes off, it'll be just what Dervahl promised.
Smoke will darken the sun as the city goes up in flames.
If we can get rid of it somehow, the blast will be much smaller.
It looks like a wooden bracket, not very strong.
Help me push this out.
Okay.
Brute force.
I'm good at that.
What'll it do?
Save the city, I hope.
But when the Blaze falls, run for it.
Because the booby trap on the bomb downstairs is gonna get set off.
Uh, will we survive?
Probably not.
Now push!
We did it!
Dervahl's best shot and Meridian's still standing.
This isn't over, Dervahl said he'd make Avad watch.
No way!
To do that he'd have to get into the palace, and that's too heavily guarded.
Get back there just to be sure.
I'm going to look around.
Maybe Dervahl's men left something behind when they planted that bomb.
I got it, don't worry.
He tries for the palace, he's finished.
Boot tracks, with just a bit of Blaze in them.
[Carja outlander]
Hope no-one was inside the warehouse when it blew.
[Vilgund]
Can I interest you in a reasonable share of a lucrative opportunity?
[Carja guard]
Did the Nora have something to do with the explosion?
[Carja outlander]
Call the guards! There could be explosions elsewhere.
[Carja merchant]
What happened?
I haven't heard a blast like that since the liberation.
[Carja merchant]
Everyone needs a splash of colour in their lives.
Come, let's talk it over.
[Carja outlander]
Blasted Shadow Carja, traitors and backstabbers…
There's smoke rising from the edge of the mesa!
[Carja outlander]
Are we under attack?
[Carja artisan]
Praise the sun! The ceasefire seems to be holding.
The tracks lead inside.
Another one of Dervahl's hideouts?
This must be where Dervahl assembled the detonator.
He tunnelled through the wall!
Dervahl did find a way into the palace.
Dervahl!
Keep that for later.
Look at you, Avad.
The wriggling runt of a maniac king!
You robbed me of my right to kill your father.
So I'll have to settle for you.
I'm going to enjoy watching the Carja burn,
even more because you'll be watching with me.
Say goodbye to Meridian, Avad.
Breathe in the stench, and choke on the ashes.
Something's wrong.
It didn't, I didn't hear anything.
There's a bit of smoke rising from the mesa's edge.
No! It should be a firestorm, not some belch from a charcoal burner.
What's this? Oh.
You must be the Nora who bushwhacked my camp.
And disabled your bomb.
[Dervahl]
Did you now?
Well, bomb or no bomb, I'm going to splatter that throne with blood.
First yours, then Avad's.
Look out, it's her!
Why does Avad always have his ladies do the fighting?
It's not over yet, Nora.
Any good Oseram tinker will tell you: always have a third plan.
Okay…
I hope you like fighting these things because there's more on the way.
Keep quiet now.
I can't spare the weight.
As much as I wish Ersa was here to kill you, I don't mind doing it for her.
Go ahead, I'm not afraid.
Except that knowing you, Erend, you'll screw it up!
I know what you are afraid of.
Going back to Mainspring in chains.
Every clan in The Claim wants you dead, and they know how to make it hurt.
They'll even bid for the privilege.
It's just like you to get someone else to do your killing.
Shut up! You're at the Sun-King's mercy now.
Aloy.
To say you have my gratitude feels woefully insufficient.
You saved my life.
You saved Meridian.
And because of you, there will be justice for Ersa's murder.
We can mourn her knowing the truth without painful uncertainty.
Were you and Ersa, you know…?
I suppose it's obvious how I feel, how I felt, about her.
She didn't just give me advice.
She gave me strength.
But we couldn't be together.
Relations between the Carja and Oseram in Meridian were unsteady as it was.
A union of the Sun-King and an Oseram warrior
would have led to open revolt in the city.
And probably war with the clans.
Did anyone know?
Only one. Dervahl.
He wanted Ersa, but she rejected him.
And so jealousy became yet another of his hateful motivations.
What a waste.
Dervahl was a brilliant man.
I wonder what he would have accomplished if it weren't for my father's cruelty.
It's time for me to go.
I will be forever grateful to you, Aloy.
It's hard to imagine where we'd be without you.
And I don't want to try.
I hope you will consider staying in Meridian.
Thank you for the offer.
But I've got a long way to go before I find what I'm looking for.
And it's gonna take me far from Meridian.
Remember that you're always welcome here.
I hope that today is just a sunrise for us.
Not a goodbye.
Why do you want me to stay in Meridian?
I would think that would be obvious.
Not to me.
Well, to start with, you kept the city from going up in flames.
You're strong, shrewd, and capable.
I could use someone like you at my side.
It might be worth taking a moment to examine what you just said.
You just lost Ersa.
A woman who stood at your side and could
easily be described as strong, shrewd, and capable.
It's pretty clear how you felt about her.
And now you're asking me to take her place?
Is this a job offer or a proposition?
By the Sun, you do indeed share much with Ersa.
Including a withering eye for foolishness.
Please accept my apologies.
Seems I'm getting ahead of myself.
I need some time to resolve my feelings.
I hope you find what you're after Aloy, and if need be I will come to your aid.
As sure as the Sun's rising.
Aloy.
I was just thinking about Ersa.
She would've killed Dervahl on the spot, I know it.
That's why she went out to meet him in the first place, to put him down.
But she also told me to grow up.
I gotta admit it burned a little when she said that.
But I'm trying to take it to heart.
And I guess growing up means putting what you should do
in front of what you want to do, right?
You're asking me? I'm pretty sure you're older.
Yeah, but I don't act like it, do I?
You did with Dervahl.
Don't give me too much credit.
Part of me still wants to wait for a quiet moment and wring his neck.
Yeah, but you won't, because you're a good captain.
Come on, stop.
You're gonna make me tear up.
So after all this, what's next for Erend Vanguardsman?
Heading back to The Claim for a while.
I'll get in touch with my clan and we'll lay Ersa to rest properly.
Like how she would have wanted.
And by that I mean less chit-chat, more drinking.
What do you think the Oseram will do to Dervahl?
First off, they'll argue about it for a long time.
But whatever they come up with, it won't be quick.
I can live with that.
In fact, I might just drop by his cell under the Sun Ring to remind him what's coming.
Well…
I know, you got to go.
Killers to track, machines to master, all before breakfast.
You know what?
When we met, I thought I was a big shot talking to
a pretty girl hidden away in the middle of nowhere.
Now I see that I was just lucky to get a minute of your time.
Try not to forget about me while you're out there changing the world.
I'll always have a minute for you.
Maybe even two.
Two? Huh, she likes me.
[Carja guard]
[yawn] No, I'm awake and alert.
[Carja merchant]
I've got all the best goods here.
I have a matter of grace and beauty I would like to discuss with you.
[Carja merchant]
You'll regret not stopping when you're in the thick of it.
[Oseram worker]
Wheel turning all day. By the forge, I believe I've earned a drink or two!
[Carja merchant]
You won't find better wares.
[Carja merchants]
- Don't pass up these goods!
- You won't find better wares.
[Carja noble]
My family might still be alive and you're going to stand here and do nothing?
[Carja guard]
We've lost a dozen patrols beyond the valley. Our orders are clear, no more.
Freeholds were warned.
[Carja noble]
You're talking about orders. I'm talking about lives!
[Carja guard]
That's what the orders are for, to save lives.
Good day, citizen.